As a kid, I was fascinated with all things air and space.
وأنا طفل، كنت مفتونا بكل ما هو جوي وفضائي.
I would watch Nova on PBS.
كنت أشاهد برنامج نوفا على PBS.
Our school would show Bill Nye the Science Guy.
ومدرستنا كانت تعرض بيل ناي "رجل العلوم".
When I was in elementary school, my next door neighbor,
عندما كنت في المدرسة الابتدائية، أعطاني
he gave me a book for my birthday.
جاري كتابا في عيد ميلادي.
It was an astronomy book,
كان كتاب علم فلك،
and I poured over that thing for hours on end,
وقد حدقت فيه لساعات دون توقف،
and it was a combination of all these things
وقد كان مزيجا من كل هذه الأشياء
that inspired me to pursue space exploration
التي أوحت لي بالسعي لاستكشاف الفضاء
as my own personal dream, and part of that dream was,
كحلمي الشخصي، وجزء من هذا الحلم كان،
I always wanted to just fly around the solar system
أنني لطالما أردت أن أطير حول النظام الشمسي
and visit different planets and visit moons and spacecraft.
وأزور الكواكب المختلفة والأقمار والمركبات الفضائية.
Well, a number of years later, I graduated from UCLA
حسنا، بعد عدة سنوات، تخرجت من جامعة كالفورنيا- لوس أنجلوس
and I found myself at NASA,
ووجدت نفسي في ناسا،
working for the jet propulsion laboratory,
أعمل في مختبر الدفع النفاث،
and there our team was challenged
وهناك تم تحدي فريقنا
to create a 3D visualization of the solar system,
لإنشاء معاينة ثلاثية الأبعاد للنظام الشمسي،
and today I want to show you what we've done so far.
وأود اليوم أن أعرض عليكم ما فعلناه حتى الآن.
Now, the kicker is, everything I'm about to do here
الآن، المثير أن كل ما أنا على وشك القيام به هنا
you can do at home, because we built this
يمكن القيام به في منزلك، لأننا بنينا هذا
for the public for you guys to use.
للعموم ولكم لتستخدموها.
So what you're looking at right now is the Earth.
حسنا ما تنظر إليه الآن هو الأرض.
You can see the United States and California
يمكنك أن ترى الولايات المتحدة وكاليفورنيا
and San Diego, and you can use the mouse
وسان دييغو، ويمكنك استخدام الفأرة
or the keyboard to spin things around.
أو لوحة المفاتيح لإدارة الأشياء.
Now, this isn't new. Anyone who's used Google Earth
الآن، هذا ليس جديدا. أي شخص يستخدم غوغل إيرث
has seen this before, but one thing we like to say
قد رآى هذا من قبل، ولكن نود أن نقول شيئا واحدا
in our group is, we do the opposite of Google Earth.
في مجموعتنا، نقوم بعكس ما يقوم به غوغل إيرث.
Google Earth goes from this view down to your backyard.
غوغل إيرث ينتقل من هذه الرؤية وصولاً إلى فنائك الخلفي.
We go from this view out to the stars.
نذهب من هذه الرؤية إلى النجوم.
So the Earth is cool, but what we really want to show
فالأرض رائعة، ولكن ما نريد حقاً أن نظهره
are the spacecraft,
هو المركبة الفضائية،
so I'm going to bring the interface back up,
لذا سأعيد إظهار الواجهة مرة أخرى،
and now you're looking at a number of satellites
وأنت ترى الآن عددا من الأقمار الاصطناعية
orbiting the Earth.
تدور حول الأرض.
These are a number of our science space Earth orbiters.
هذه مجموعة من الأقمار الباحثة في الأرض والعلم.
We haven't included military satellites and weather satellites
لم نشمل الأقمار العسكرية وأقمار الطقس
and communication satellites and reconnaissance satellites.
وأقمار الاتصالات وأقمار الاستطلاع.
If we did, it would be a complete mess,
إن فعلنا ذلك، فإنه ستعم الفوضى،
because there's a lot of stuff out there.
لأن هناك الكثير من الأشياء هناك.
And the cool thing is, we actually created 3D models
والأمر الرائع هو أننا فعلا أنشأنا نماذج ثلاثية الأبعاد
for a number of these spacecraft, so if you want to visit
لعدد من هذه المركبات الفضائية، لذا إذا كنت ترغب في زيارة
any of these, all you need to do is double-click on them.
أي من هذه، كل ما عليك القيام به هو أن تنقر بازدواجية عليها.
So I'm going to find the International Space Station,
سأبحث عن محطة الفضاء الدولية،
double-click, and it will take us all the way down to the ISS.
نقرة مزدوجة، وسوف توصلنا إلى المحطة الفضائية الدولية (ISS).
And now you're riding along with the ISS
وستركب جنبا إلى جنب مع ISS
where it is right now.
حيث هي الآن.
And the other cool thing is, not only can we
والأمر الآخر الرائع، وليس فقط أنه يمكننا
move the camera around, we can also control time,
تحريك آلة التصوير، نستطيع أيضا التحكم في الوقت،
so I can slide this jog dial here
أستطيع سحب هذا الشيء هنا
to shuttle time forward, and now
لتحريك الوقت نحو الأمام، والآن
we can see what a sunset on the ISS would look like,
يمكننا أن نرى ما الذي يبدو عليه غروب الشمس في ISS،
and they get one every 90 minutes. (Laughter)
ويحصل لديهم كل 90 دقيقة. (ضحك)
All right, so what about the rest of it?
حسنا، ماذا عن بقيته؟
Well, I can click on this home button over here,
حسنا، أستطيع أن أضغط على زر الصفحة الرئيسية هنا،
and that will take us up to the inner solar system,
وهذا سوف يأخذنا إلى النظام الشمسي الداخلي،
and now we're looking at the rest of the solar system.
والآن نحن ننظر إلى بقية النظام الشمسي.
You can see, there's Saturn, there's Jupiter,
يمكنك أن ترى، هناك زحل، وهناك المشتري،
and while we're here, I want to point out something.
ونحن هنا، أريد أن أشير إلى شيء.
It's actually pretty busy.
إنه في الواقع مشغول جداً.
Here we have the Mars Science Laboratory
هنا لدينا "مختبر علوم المريخ"
on its way to Mars, just launched last weekend.
في طريقه إلى المريخ، تم اطلاقه في نهاية الأسبوع الماضي فقط.
Here we have Juno on its cruise to Jupiter, there.
هنا لدينا جونو في رحلته نحو المشتري، هناك.
We have Dawn orbiting Vesta,
ولدينا داون يدور حول فيستا،
and we have over here New Horizons
وهنا لدينا "نيو هورايزونز"
on a straight shot to Pluto.
على خط مستقيم نحو بلوتو.
And I mention this because
وأذكر هذا لأن
there's this strange public perception that
لأنه يعم تصور عام غريب أن
NASA's dead, that the space shuttles stopped flying
ناسا ميتة، أن المكوكات الفضائية توقفت عن التحليق
and all of the sudden there's no more spacecraft out there.
وفجأة لم تعد هناك أي مركبة فضائية.
Well, a lot of what NASA does is robotic exploration,
حسنا، الكثير مما تقوم به ناسا هو استكشافات روبوتية،
and we have a lot of spacecraft out there.
ولدينا الكثير من المركبات الفضائية هناك.
Granted, we're not sending humans up at the moment,
صحيح، لا نرسل بشرا حاليا،
well at least with our own launch vehicles,
حسنا على الأقل في مركبات الإطلاق الخاصة بنا،
but NASA is far from dead,
ولكن ناسا أبعد ما تكون عن الموت،
and one of the reasons why we write a program like this
وأحد الأسباب التي تجعلنا نكتب مثل هذا البرنامج
is so that people realize that there's so many other things
هو ليدرك الناس أن هناك الكثير من الأشياء الأخرى
that we're doing.
نقوم بها.
Anyway, while we're here, again,
على كل حال، بينما نحن هنا، مجددا،
if you want to visit anything,
إذا كنت ترغب في زيارة أي مكان،
all you need to do is double-click.
كل ما عليك القيام به هو النقر بشكل مزدوج عليه.
So I'm just going to double-click on Vesta,
لذلك سأقوم فقط بالنقر بشكل مزدوج على فيستا،
and here we have Dawn orbiting Vesta,
وهنا لدينا داون وهو يدور حول فيستا،
and this is happening right now.
وهذا يحدث الآن.
I'm going to double-click on Uranus, and we can see
سأنقر بشكل مزدوج مجددا على أورانوس، ويمكننا أن نرى
Uranus rotating on its side along with its moons.
أورانوس يدور على جانبه جنبا إلى جنب مع أقماره.
You can see how it's tilted at about 89 degrees.
يمكنك أن ترى كيف أنه مائل بحوالي 89 درجة.
And just being able to visit different places
ومجرد التمكن من زيارة أماكن مختلفة
and go through different times,
والتنقل خلال أوقات مختلفة،
we have data from 1950 to 2050.
لدينا بيانات من سنة 1950 إلى 2050.
Granted, we don't have everything in between,
صحيح أنه ليس لدينا كل شيء بينهما،
because some of the data is hard to get.
لأنه من الصعب الحصول على بعض البيانات.
Just being able to visit places in different times,
مجرد التمكن من زيارة الأماكن في أوقات مختلفة،
you can explore this for hours,
يمكنك استكشاف هذا لساعات،
literally hours on end,
حرفيا لساعات دون توقف،
but I want to show you one thing in particular,
ولكن أريد أن أريكم شيئا واحدا على وجه الخصوص،
so I'm going to open up the destination tab,
سأقوم بفتح علامة تبويب الوجهة،
spacecraft outer planet missions, Voyager 1,
بعثات مركبات الفضاء خارج الكواكب، فوياجر 1،
and I'm going to bring up the Titan flyby.
وسأظهر فليبي التايتان.
So now we've gone back in time.
لذا فنحن الآن قد عدنا في الزمن.
We're now riding along with Voyager 1.
نحن الآن جنبا إلى جنب مع فوياجر 1.
The date here is November 11, 1980.
التاريخ هنا هو 11 نوفمبر 1980.
Now, there's a funny thing going on here.
الآن، ليس هناك شيء مضحك يحدث هنا.
It doesn't look like anything's going on.
لا يبدو أن أي شيء يحدث.
It looks like I've paused the program.
يبدو وكأنني أوقفت البرنامج مؤقتاً.
It's actually running at real rate right now,
وهو الآن يشتغل بالمعدل الحقيقي،
one second per second, and in fact,
ثانية بثانية، وفي الحقيقة،
Voyager 1 here is flying by Titan at
فوياجر 1 هنا تحلق قرب تيتان بسرعة
I think it's 38,000 miles per hour.
أعتقد أنها تعادل 38,000 ميلا في الساعة.
It only looks like nothing's moving because, well,
يبدو فقط أنه لا شيء يتحرك لأنه، حسنا،
Saturn here is 700,000 miles away,
زحل هنا على بعد 700,000 ميل،
and Titan here is 4,000 to 5,000 miles away.
وتيتان هنا على بعد 4,000 إلى 5,000 ميل.
It's just the vastness of space makes it look like nothing's happening.
شساعة الفضاء فقط تجعله يبدو وكأنه لا شيء يحدث.
But to make it more interesting,
ولكن لجعلها أكثر إثارة للاهتمام،
I'm going to speed up time, and we can watch
سأقوم بتسريع الوقت، ويمكن أن نشاهد
as Voyager 1 flies by Titan,
فوياجر 1 يحلق قرب تايتان،
which is a hazy moon of Saturn.
والذي هو قمر ضبابي لكوكب زحل.
It actually has a very thick atmosphere.
ولديه في الواقع غلاف جوي سميك للغاية.
And I'm going to recenter the camera on Saturn, here.
وسأقوم بإعادة تركيز آلات التصوير على زحل هنا.
I'm going to pull out, and I want to show you
وسأنسحب، وأنا أريد أن أريكم
Voyager 1 as it flies by Saturn.
فوياجر 1 وهو يحلق بجوار زحل.
There's a point to be made here.
هناك نقطة ينبغي الإشارة إليها هنا.
With a 3D visualization like this,
مع مرئيات ثلاثيات الأبعاد كهذه،
we can not only just say Voyager 1 flew by Saturn.
لا يمكننا إلا مجرد القول أن فوياجر 1 حلق بجوار زحل.
There's a whole story to tell here.
هناك قصة كاملة لنرويها هنا.
And even better, because it's an interactive application,
لكن بشكل أفضل، ولأنه تطبيق تفاعلي،
you can tell the story for yourself.
يمكن أن تروي القصة بنفسك.
If you want to pause it, you can pause it.
إذا كنت ترغب في إيقاف تشغيله مؤقتاً، يمكنك ذلك.
If you want to keep going, if you want to change
إذا كنت ترغب في الاستمرار، إذا كنت ترغب في تغيير
the camera angle, you can do that,
زاوية آلة التصوير، يمكنك ذلك،
and because of that, I can show you
ولذلك، يمكن أن أريكم
that Voyager 1 doesn't just fly by Saturn.
أن فوياجر 1 لا يحلق فقط بجوار زحل.
It actually flies underneath Saturn.
هو في الواقع يحلق تحت زحل.
Now, what happens is, as it flies underneath Saturn,
الآن، ما يحدث هو، وهو يحلق تحت زحل،
Saturn grabs it gravitationally and flings it up
يجتذبه زحل ويدفعه صعودا
and out of the solar system,
وخارج النظام الشمسي،
so if I just keep letting this go,
ولذا إن واصلت على نفس المنوال،
you can see Voyager 1 fly up like that.
يمكنك أن ترى فوياجر 1 يطير هكذا.
And, in fact, I'm going to go back to the solar system.
وفي الواقع، سأعود إلى النظام الشمسي.
I'm going to go back to today, now,
سأعود إلى اليوم، الآن،
and I want to show you where Voyager 1 is.
وأنا أريد أن أريكم أين هو فوياجر 1.
Right there, above, way above the solar system,
هناك تماما، في الأعلى، في أعلى النظام الشمسي،
way beyond our solar system.
بعيدا جدا عن نظامنا الشمسي.
And here's the thing. Now you know how it got there.
وهذا ما في الأمر. الآن تعرف كيف وصل إلى هناك.
Now you know why, and to me,
الآن تعرف لماذا، وبالنسبة لي،
that's the point of this program.
هذه هي الغاية من هذا البرنامج.
You can manipulate it yourself.
ويمكنك التلاعب به بنفسك.
You can fly around yourself and you can learn for yourself.
يمكنك أن تطير حول نفسك، ويمكنك أن تتعلم بنفسك.
You know, the theme today is "The World In Your Grasp."
تعلمون، الموضوع اليوم هو "العالم في متناول يدك."
Well, we're trying to give you
حسنا، نحن نحاول أن نجعل
the solar system in your grasp — (Laughter) —
النظام الشمسي في متناول يدك — (ضحك) —
and we hope once it's there,
ويحدونا الأمل أنه بمجرد أنها هناك،
you'll be able to learn for yourself
ستكون قادرا على التعلم بنفسك
what we've done out there, and what we're about to do.
ما قمنا به هناك، وما نحن على وشك القيام به.
And my personal dream is for kids to take this
وحلمي الشخصي هو أن يأخذ الأطفال هذا
and explore and see the wonders out there
ويستكشفوا وينظروا إلى العجائب هناك
and be inspired, as I was as a kid,
وأن يتم إلهامهم، كما أنا حين كنت طفلا،
to pursue STEM education
ومتابعة التعليم في تخصصات STEM (العلوم والتكنولوجيا والهندسة والرياضيات)
and to pursue a dream in space exploration.
وتحقيق حلم استكشاف الفضاء.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)